<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes" ?> <!-- Conserve vertical whitespace -->
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902"
docName="draft-procter-dispatch-outbound-unaptr-latest">

    <front>
        <title abbrev="Discovering outbound proxies">
			Automatic discovery of RFC 5626 Edge Proxies using U-NAPTR
        </title>
        <author initials="M." surname="Procter"
                fullname="Michael Procter">
            <address>
                <email>michael.ietf@gmail.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Olle E. Johansson" initials="O. E"
                surname="Johansson">
          <organization>Edvina AB</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>Runbov&auml;gen 10</street>

              <city>Sollentuna</city>

              <code>SE-192 48</code>

              <country>SE</country>
            </postal>

            <email>oej@edvina.net</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <date day="DAY" month="MONTH" year="YEAR"/>

        <workgroup>DISPATCH</workgroup>

        <abstract><t>

<xref target="RFC5626"/> (commonly known as 'SIP outbound') defines
mechanisms that permit SIP (Session Initiation Protocol) UAs (User
Agents) to maintain multiple connections to a registrar or proxy via
multiple Edge Proxies, known as the outbound-proxy-set.  Discovering
the URIs that make up the outbound-proxy-set is left to configuration
or future discovery mechanisms.
</t>
<t>
This draft defines a simple discovery mechanism based on U-NAPTR
<xref target="RFC4848"/> that enables UAs to discover the URIs of all the 
Edge Proxies in the outbound-proxy-set without requiring additional 
configuration on the UA.

</t></abstract>
    </front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
<t>
Reliably maintaining connectivity between a SIP UA and a registrar
across the Internet, in the presence of NATs, routing changes,
and maintenance of intervening equipment is made more straightforward
by <xref target="RFC5626"/>.  The mechanisms in that specification allow
multiple connections over diverse routes, equipment, and data centres,
which permit a more robust SIP service to be created.
</t>
<t>
However, one of the hurdles that is preventing wide-spread use of these
mechanisms is discovering the outbound-proxy-set, the list of suitable
edge proxies that a UA may use for multiple connections.  Some UAs
permit this set to be configured, but the large number of options
available on many UAs means that configuration for robustness is often
overlooked once basic operation is possible.
</t>
<t>
This draft describes a simple mechanism by which a UA may 
determine the outbound-proxy-set from the DNS.  The choice of U-NAPTR
<xref target="RFC4848"/> is driven by the desire to directly discover
URIs to use as outbound proxies, yet also minimise the complexity of the
solution by not requiring the regular expression processing associated
with a full NAPTR implementation.
</t>
</section>

<section title="User Agent Behaviour" anchor="usage">
<section title="Determining the outbound-proxy-set">
<t>When a UA wishes to determine the outbound-proxy-set for a particular
domain (the domain against which it wishes to register), it 
submits a DNS NAPTR query for that domain.
</t>
<figure>
<preamble>
For example, when registering against 'sip:example.net', the UA would
submit a DNS NAPTR query for "example.net", and might receive a response
contains answers such as:
</preamble>
<artwork>
   NAPTR 100 10 "u" "SIPOUTBOUND" "!^.*$!sips:lon.example.net!" ""
   NAPTR 100 10 "u" "SIPOUTBOUND" "!^.*$!sips:nyc.example.net!" ""
   NAPTR 100 20 "u" "SIPOUTBOUND" "!^.*$!sips:cph.example.net!" ""
   NAPTR 100 30 "u" "SIPOUTBOUND" "!^.*$!sips:sfo.example.net!" ""
   NAPTR  90 50 "s" "SIP+D2T"     ""  _sip._tcp.example.net.
   NAPTR 100 50 "s" "SIP+D2U"     ""  _sip._udp.example.net.

</artwork>
</figure>
<t>
In this example, four SIP URIs with an application service tag of
"SIPOUTBOUND" are provided with the same order and varying preference
values.  A UA may use as many of these as it supports in preference order
as the outbound-proxy-set.  <xref target="RFC5626"/> requires UAs to
support at least two and preferably up to four outbound-proxies.
</t>
<t>TODO: should we use both application service and protocol tags,
e.g. "OUTBOUND:sip" &amp; "OUTBOUND:sips", or just a service tag as shown?
</t>
<t>TODO: Is it worth noting we can only use answers with the same order
value?  rfc3403 is very clear that you can't consider answers with
different orders.
</t>

<t>
Following the construction of the outbound-proxy-set, the procedures in
<xref target="RFC5626"/> section 4 may be followed.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Maintaining the outbound-proxy-set">
<t>Since the outbound-proxy-set is now determined dynamically, rather
than through static configuration, care should be taken to respect the
relevant DNS TTL values and ensure that when the DNS
records change, the configuration of the outbound-proxy-set and the 
number and destinations of registrations are updated accordingly.
</t>
<t>If the outbound-proxy-set is refreshed and no changes are found, then
the UA continues to use the flows it has already established.  If it has
a flow to a proxy that is no longer present in the outbound-proxy-set,
it should take steps to remove that flow.  Similarly, if additional proxies
are now available, the UA may choose to establish flows to these proxies.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<!--section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
</t>
</section-->

<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec_cons">
<t>
TODO
</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
   This section contains the registration information for one U-NAPTR
   application service tag
<!-- and two U-NAPTR application protocol tags -->
   (in accordance with <xref target="RFC4848"/>).
</t>

<section title="SIP-Outbound Application Service Tag Registration">
<t>
   Application Protocol Tag: SIPOUTBOUND
</t>
<t>
   Intended usage: See <xref target="usage"/>.
</t>
<t>
   Interoperability considerations: N/A
</t>
<t>
   Security considerations: See <xref target="sec_cons"/>.
</t>
<t>
   Relevant related publications: <xref target="RFC5626"/>.
</t>
</section>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
        <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5626'?>
        <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4848'?>
    </references>
    <!--<references title="Informative References">
    </references> -->
</back>
</rfc>
<!-- vim:set ts=4 et tw=72:  -->
